{"tossups": [{"question": "Temur Khan sent Zhou Da Guan to this modern-day country to describe its customs. Baphuon and Bayon are temples in this country, where Henri Mouhot explored ruins of a Buddhist temple. This country contains the freshwater lake of Tonle S\u00b4ap, which is connected to the Mekong River. Jayavarman II ruled the Khmer Empire in what is now this country. The Khmer Rouge established \u201ckilling fields\u201d in, for the point, what southeast Asian country once ruled by Pol Pot?", "answer": "<b> Cambodia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Rawson Macharia claimed that this leader required him to strip naked and drink human blood. This leader arrested Oginga Odinga, the leader of the rival KPU party, in 1969. This leader, who promoted the policy of Harambee, was tried as part of the Kapenguria Six for his role in the Mau Mau Rebellion. This predecessor of Daniel Arap Moi wrote about his homeland in his study of the Kikuyu people. For the point, name this first president of independent Kenya.", "answer": "Jomo<b> Kenyatta</b> (accept<b> Kamau</b> wa Ngengi; accept Johnstone<b> Kamau</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist\u2019s album art includes a 1986 block-colored portrait of Aretha Franklin and a banana cover for<em> The Velvet Underground & Nico</em>, whom this artist included in his Exploding Plastic Inevitable show. This artist\u2019s<em> Flowers</em> was copied by Sturtevant, using this artist\u2019s original silkscreens. This artist painted wood<em> Brillo Boxes</em>, which appeared alongside silkscreens of commercial objects. For the point, name this American Pop artist famed for his Campbell\u2019s Soup Cans.", "answer": "Andy<b> Warhol</b> (accept Andrew<b> Warhola</b>, Jr)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A politician from this state was nominated for president at a convention where Richard Daley was compared to the Gestapo; that senator from this state lost to Richard Nixon in the general election. Another senator from this state was badly beaten in the 1984 presidential election by Ronald Reagan. The Democratic and Farmer-Labor parties are combined in, for the point, what home state of Hubert Humphrey and Walter Mondale whose capital is Saint Paul?", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Daily Thermometer</em> cites a figure in this event shouting \u201cI am lost!\u201d Before this event, Henry Essex Edgeworth met with its central figure for confession. The Baron de Betz tried to stop this event, in which an anonymous Freemason may have shouted, \u201cJacques de Molay, thou art avenged!\u201d This event occurred at the<em> Place de la Concorde</em> a week after a quick trial at the National Convention. For the point, name this January 21, 1793 event, a regicide by guillotine during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> execution of Louis XVI</b> [16] (accept equivalent descriptions of the<b> death</b> of<b> Louis XVI</b>; prompt on partial answers, such as \u201cbeheading the French king\u201d and \u201cdeath of Louis\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man argued that evidence obtained during an illegal search was inadmissible in the Silverthorne Lumber case, forming the \u201cfruit of the poisonous tree\u201d doctrine. In defense of forced sterilizations, this man wrote \u201cthree generations of imbeciles is enough\u201d in his majority opinion in<em> Buck v. Bell</em>. The First Amendment does not protect someone from yelling \u201cfire!\u201d in a movie theatre according to, for the point, what Supreme Court justice\u2019s ruling in<em> Schenck v. U.S.</em>?", "answer": "Oliver Wendell<b> Holmes</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s son Samsu-iluna failed to hold most of this ruler\u2019s conquests. Some scholars have argued that this ruler was King Amraphel from the Book of Genesis or that Moses copied this ruler\u2019s work. This ruler, the most ancient figure portrayed on the Supreme Court\u2019s south wall and the US Capitol\u2019s plaques of lawgivers, promoted<em> lex talionis</em> by dictating \u201ca tooth for a tooth\u201d and \u201can eye for an eye.\u201d For the point, name this king of the First Babylonian Dynasty, best known for his law code.", "answer": "<b> Hammurabi</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "An earlier One holder of this position had his advisor, Schabir Shaik, convicted of fraud in 2005. An earlier holder of this position established the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, whose subpoena was ignored by another holder, P.W. Botha. One person in this position, F.W. de Klerk, allowed universal suffrage and freed a political prisoner from Robben Island. For the point, name this political position held by ANC party members like Jacob Zuma and Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "<b> President</b> of<b> South Africa</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cPresident\u201d or \u201cleader of South Africa\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man gained control of the Dalmatian coastline after launching repeated sieges of Shkodra. Over 20,000 of this man\u2019s troops were killed and displayed on stakes at Targoviste after he suffered a setback in the \u201cNight Attack.\u201d This man was more successful at a battle where he commissioned Orban to build the large Dardanelles cannon. This man\u2019s defeat of Constantine XI and capture of the Bosphorus earned him the epithet \u201cConqueror.\u201d For the point, name this Ottoman sultan who captured Constantinople in 1453.", "answer": "<b> Mehmed</b> the Conqueror (accept<b> Mehmed</b> II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the speech announcing this policy, its namesake stated that \u201cthe late events in Spain and Portugal show that Europe is still unsettled.\u201d In 1833, a failure to act on this policy angered Argentina after the United Kingdom reaffirmed its claims on the Falkland Islands. Simon Bolivar appreciated this policy, but understood that the United States ultimately could not stand against European powers to enforce it. For the point, name this policy that stated the Americas were off-limits for European colonization, issued by the 5th President of the United States.", "answer": "<b> Monroe Doctrine</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In 593 AD, Soga no Umako ordered relics of this religion to be buried below Asuka-dera after a relic legendarily broke a hammer and anvil. The Ikko-ikki was largely composed of militant members of this religion. The Higashiyama culture was heavily influenced by this religion and furthered the development of the Japanese tea ceremony. Korean monks spread this religion to Japan in 552 AD, and its Pure Land and Zen schools reached Japan centuries later. For the point, name this East Asian religion based on the teachings of Siddharta Gautama.", "answer": "Japanese<b> Buddhism</b> Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Laura Bullard\u2019s support for patent medicines upset this woman, who sold Bullard her newspaper in 1870. This woman protested a \u201chigh-handed outrage upon my citizen\u2019s rights\u201d after Ward Hunt ordered her to stop talking during a trial. This woman refused to pay a one hundred dollar fine, which was levied after she was arrested for attempting to vote in the 1872 elections. For the point, name this woman who founded the National Woman Suffrage Association with Elizabeth Cady Stanton.", "answer": "Susan B.<b> Anthony</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruling house came to power in one country after the death of David II in 1371, and it fell from power shortly after Mary of Modena gave birth to a son. A ruler of this house was killed at the 1513 Battle of Flodden Field. Robert Catesby and Guy Fawkes attempted the Gunpowder Plot against a ruler from, for the point, what Scottish royal house that entered a personal union with England under James the first and sixth in 1603?", "answer": "House of<b> Stuart</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, who played Quinton Locke in a film where he fights an automaton named Q, was initially but wrongly credited as the first man to fly over Australia. As a member of the<em> Scientific American</em> committee, this man debunked mediums and spiritualists in the early 20th century, eventually earning the ire of Sir Arthur Conan Doyle. This man died in 1926 after developing an inflammation in the inner wall of the abdomen after being punched without having time to brace himself. The Milk Can and Water Torture Cell were apparatuses used by, for the point, what renowned American escapist and magician?", "answer": "Harry<b> Houdini</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Soviet anthropologist Mikhail Gerasimov supposedly cursed the USSR by exhuming this man\u2019s body a few days before Operation Barbarossa. This man, who captured Sultan Bayezid the Thunderbolt at the Battle of Ankara, claimed to be a descendant of Genghis Khan and built towers of skulls after conquering Baghdad. Samarkand was the capital of, for the point, what founder of a 15th century central Asian empire who suffered from two injured limbs?", "answer": "<b> Timur</b> the Lame (or<b> Tamerlane</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this profession held by pilot Yuri Gagarin, the first man in space.", "answer": "<b> cosmonaut</b>s (prompt on descriptions of (Russian/Soviet) astronauts) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country gave up the Great and Little Corn Islands to the U.S. in the Bryan-Chamorro Treaty. The Boland Amendment prevented the US from assisting rebels in this country. American filibuster William Walker became president of this country in 1854. A president of this country took charge of its socialist Sandinista party, which overthrew dictator Anastasio Somoza. The United States used Middle Eastern arms sales to fund Contras in, for the point, what country where Daniel Ortega leads from Managua?", "answer": "<b> Nicaragua</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first X-ray telescope put into space was named for this scientist, who wrote a letter with Leo Szilard [seh-LARD] warning about the dangers of atomic bombs. This man won the Nobel Prize for his explanation of the photoelectric effect, which was among the four papers published in 1905, a year known as his \u201cAnnus Mirabilis.\u201d For the point, name this scientist who formulated a mass-energy relation commonly written as E equals m c squared.", "answer": "Albert<b> Einstein</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "This country was the target of five failed raids by the Fenian Brotherhood. Benedict Arnold led troops up the Kennebec River in an attack against this country that was coordinated with Richard Montgomery\u2019s capture of a major city here in 1775. While defending this country, General Isaac Brock died at the Battle of Queenston Heights, an early major battle of the War of 1812. For the point, name this British-controlled country that faced several invasion attempts by its neighbor to the south, the United States.", "answer": "<b> Canada</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}